so hi my name is Joe brewer and I have
been writing a lot recently about the
mental disease of late stage capitalism
how to deal with the crises that are
just coming one after another in the
world today the feelings of loneliness
and isolation that arise around
individualistic cultures and economic
ideologies and political philosophies
and the effects that they have on us and
what I want to do now is just be a
little bit more personal and share with
you some of my experiences as I've been
writing these things and the responses
that I've been getting so first off in
case you're wondering if you read some
of my work recently I'm actually a very
happy and upbeat person and so I I'm the
kind of person who I like taking off my
friends and be suit be silly and goofy
and I'm a dancer and I like to move even
tall like the way I'm recording this
video I'm like I don't sit still very
well you know I I like to be up and
moving and so what does it mean for
someone who's upbeat and energetic and
exciting about the world to step back
and do with the immense trauma that all
of us are going through right now and to
feel into that and so here's the thing
first of all we live in a world that is
designed around the outcomes we're
getting so there's something really
empowering and saying the economy is not
broken it's fixed it has been built
brick by brick policy by policy to take
wealth from the productive activities of
everyday people and accumulate it in the
hands of yardie bitch this is not like
some big mistake it's not that people
are too stupid to figure out how to do
it right it's that there were some
people who were smart enough to figure
out how to make this system work for
themselves and that's actually really
inspiring in spite of the kind of
conspiratorial feel
because what it says is that if a group
of people over time can build up their
policy frameworks in a way that create
wealth and security in the consolidation
of power then that means that the much
larger community of the rest of us who
collectively hold much much more
knowledge and expertise than the small
group of people ever could imagine
happening
having that if we just coordinate our
actions in the right way we just find
the right ways to cooperate we will be
smarter faster more agile more creative
than these people who have been rigging
our systems see that the whole thing
about like the surveillance state what
Edward Snowden showed us and how there
the need to surveil people and imprison
people to stop them from speaking truth
about what's going on and to have that
information become privatized so that a
small set of people can benefit from it
well no one else does well what that
says is that the people who have been
gaming the system have been gaming it
not by being innovative they've been
doing it by siphoning off the value of
innovation closing it off where they
find it so if we have ways to open it up
to make it more inclusive to let more
people participate in it
to have actual open markets rather than
closed monopolistic feudalistic
oligarchies were basically the people
who set up the rules of the market
rigged it to benefit themselves and the
larger the actors are in this space the
more they distort the market toward
their own ends rather than that we can
invite envision things like the
tremendous abundance coming out of
robotics in manufacturing today means we
don't have to produce and consume as
much crap and do as much damage to the
environment and that more people can get
access to it if only we have the kind of
social values of openness participation
trust the belief that everyone deserves
to have a chance and the prosperity
should be shared
and that those who help to create value
should benefit and the and the value
that is created now these are not even
crazy rocket science ideas these are
everyday human relationship ideas you
see that the truth of the matter is that
if we look back in our history in the
scientists who study human evolution can
tell you this with you know countless
books and stories there's so much
research on this now human beings were
profoundly social deeply incredibly
social we depend on each other we live
in groups were born vulnerable and need
caretakers to take care of us we know
almost nothing about how to get in wrap
get around in our environments unless
our cultures teach it to us you see we
are we are a kind of animal that
throughout its long history has figured
out how to be strong by being in
communities so something that we're good
at and we thrive that and you see it
every time there's an earthquake or a
tornado or a volcano every time there's
a natural disaster people's compassion
comes out their ability to break out of
their standard roles and create an
invent in the moment to support and help
each other it's just incredibly
inspiring the reason that we don't do it
is because there all of these systems
that have been built up to divide us to
pit us against each other to tell us
that someone over there is the enemy
when the real enemy is the systems of
division themselves so you see the more
that I have studied the problems of the
world the more I've seen that the only
way to understand the problems is to
explore and enrich your knowledge of how
much isn't known about the problems in
in that exploration in that learning we
come across a treasure trove of
solutions and so our ability to be
inspired and hopeful in this time of
crisis is really deep and it's built on
solid foundation
so yeah the world's pretty fucked up
right now there are a lot of shitty
things going on and it's hurting all of
us we are all feeling the pain of it and
yet at the same time if only we can
figure out how to trust each other and
cooperate with the people who play well
together form effective teams and come
together all the knowledge is there all
of the tools are there they're available
to us we can pick them up and we can
learn to use them and we can tackle
these challenges and actually we have
the ability to make the world a better
place than it's probably ever been
before but we have to recognize that at
the core of it all there is no such
thing as the isolated individual no man
woman or child is an island we are
deeply social animals we live in
communities we grow in communities we
even become an art become ourselves in
relationship to others but more deeply
we're also part of this world we are
part of nature so all that we find
beautiful in the world that we feel is
threatened by human activities that's
part of us we are part of it when I see
a beautiful sunset and I think the
beauty of the scene it's so gorgeous
nature is incredible
well that beauty in that aw is
experienced in the brain in the body of
this human organism that ability to
experience reverence and awe is
something that human beings are capable
of doing and maybe only a few other
animals on earth so we are the
embodiment we are nature as it is able
to experience beauty and all so if we
lose humans we just might lose that
ability and the universe might be
deprived because of it so it's not that
humans are the problem and nature will
go on without us so we are part of
nature and our big delusion has been
to not see the whore candidate do not
recognize it in a simple test to see how
much you're part of nature is hold your
breath and see how long you can go
without here how long you can get by
without food or water how long you can
get by without the knowledge that
someone else created that you use to
solve a problem in your daily life you
see we are all interdependent we are all
part of this wonderful incredible dance
that is the universe and so as I've been
writing and thinking about these things
I'm hopeful I'm not hopeful because of a
Pollyanna simplistic illusion that the
problems are easy to solve we have some
serious serious problems in this world
but the first thing we have to do before
we can ever hope to solve them is to
believe that it's possible to solve them
and to see the innate goodness in the
human existence that we can build upon
to do it so that's the message that I
wanted to share thank you for reading my
articles for listening and watching this
video and you know let's let's do this
together
as I like to say at the end of my
writings onward fellow humans